it does like an emotional thing to you I
feel the same way about the little what
reminds me of like a Nintendo DS or
something which is this like arpeggiated
love this organ I love this I think this
does so much for the it plays so quietly
it just kind of peeks out when the vocal
goes away it sounds fake sounds like a
toy barf it's like so Sentimental
Feeling I really wanted the whole thing
to sound like Animal Crossing I think
that was a
big I am Billy ish I'm Phineas and we
are going to be showing you how we made
the song What Was I made for it was one
of the the the fastest songs we've ever
written once we got that first verse and
that line just what was I made for I
think we were both
like it was a good vibe and it was
honestly like a half hour that it took
to do
[Music]
that made for this is like one of four
cases total in our career where we've
made something to then kind of submit to
people it's a different way of making
music because you're auditioning yeah
definitely an audition and all we had
was a voice memo our main concern was we
can't send them this voice memo because
was rough but there was something about
it that was cool it was pretty special I
used
know
but what I was made
for it is top three hardest songs I've
ever had to record it's not even that
it's high it is high in my range but
it's not about that it's about the
delivery I was trying to do a very
specific thing with my voice which was
this like very soft held back you know
upper range falsetto where as I could
have you know I could have belted it I
could have sung it more out I could have
sung it in like more of a Coral like
choir
type and instead it was like
a used to FL it's really hard to do like
honestly it's really hard to do it's
really hard to sound good and be
enunciating the um words correctly and
and enough having I remember that being
a big part of the song was making sure
that it was intelligible I wanted you to
understand what I was saying could have
literally done like a ah used to float
and now I but I was not that's not what
the song Wanted you know and I could
have G I used to float I there so many
ways I could have sung it but none of it
worked the way that this kind of
heartbroken almost like you were just
crying and now you're singing delivery
was and it was the hardest choice of all
of the choices I could have
[Music]
made
I had this this exact vision for what I
wanted it to sound like and I I got it
there and I feel really proud I think
it's one of the best if I can be honest
and self whatever I feel like it's one
of my best vocal performances I've ever
given but you were harsh about it she
would she we we' do the whole vocal and
comp it and we'd be working on the
production she'd go home for the night
and she'd come back the next day and
she'd be like I need to re-record this
line this line and this line when I was
starting out I had one way of singing
and that's how I sang and everything
that I sang I just sang it how I knew
how to sing it and now I have all these
choices and I can play with my like
instrument like I have an instrument now
that I can play with and it's really
amazing and it's really it's really fun
but it's definitely hard and I would say
that I don't know how to feel was brutal
cuz it goes it does that like you know
uh ascending cuz I cuz I I don't know
how to feel and it's so high and you're
kind of sliding at the note what is the
key wait for a second
[Music]
yeah I don't know how to feel that
how oh you guys I must have done that
like a gazillion time I don't know
and the oh my gosh I'm so glad it's over
I'm so glad I recorded it and I don't
have to record it again the Run was
definitely tough I think it was tough
because it's in head voice and for me
runs are much easier in kind of a lower
register in a in a in like a mid chess
[Music]
voice that was the one that came to me
initially and I really wanted to do it
but I was like I don't know if I can get
this one the second chorus was belted
for a while and that run was belted and
it just didn't sound right it just was
like this isn't what this is It's
supposed to be but of course it's much
easier to do that I was like God I have
to do the soft you
[Music]
know okay nice dude I think I'm good
that run it's intricate it what is it
cuz
[Music]
I it's fast it's soft it's back here
it's not forward Billy's ability to
double track is really amazing there's
like micro rhythms when you're double
tracking of where each syllable and
Pitch ends and begins on the lead vocal
that you've tracked and often times
especially the way that Billy sings is a
little Jazzy so often times her delivery
is behind the bead or rushing and then
behind the beat very purposeful it is
but it's but it's hard to uh hard to
double it's hard to replicate if you
sing in a very sort of like common time
all the notes starting the Down Beat
that's much easier to double and she's
doing really Jazzy intricate stuff made
[Music]
[Applause]
me to even double that is really
challenging and she'll just go after it
and and Crush that and then she's able
to do it when she harmonizes too and
she's got a big
[Music]
range
feel and that's playing at the same time
can you play with the lead though I
don't know how to
feel so even her vibr is on the same
Rhythm as the breaths are all matched up
the vibr is all matched up I
don't feel so that's three takes at
[Music]
once this is just the lead that line you
can barely hear it you can kind of just
feel it in the Imaging of it and there's
a fuging called vocal line that will
analyze a waveform and and and stretch
it and and contract it and I've never
used it once with
Billy don't know how to feel I think of
sound in a very physical way I think
that sound has a weight to it and I
think that a perfect production is like
a perfectly balanced set of scales I'm
just trying to keep the equilibrium and
I feel like generally I can feel
innately when something is tipping the
scale and sort of ruining the balance of
everything and it is it is all sort of
like placing things really delicately
and making sure that it holds and then
if it holds maybe adding something else
but often times especially from a stereo
perspective it's like if something's
going on over here something's going on
over here so that it balances I've gone
on record of saying this but like the
fantasy is that your vocal is
unbelievable and the one instrument
playing along to it the piano or the
guitar is great and that it's you know
you're like Bob Dylan and it's just that
the art part of production to me is just
to enhance the emotionality it isn't to
gild a lily or something so we just
tried to be inventive and add to the
sort of narrative components of it one
of my favorite components of the
production on this I've spent a lot of
time just handing Billy some instrument
that's in my studio because I'm more
interested in what she's going to do
experimenting with it she has less years
of standing you know behind a keyboard
on a stage than I do I don't really know
what I'm doing and that's excited as a
producer the idea that they're going to
come up with is so much less theoretical
and I love that and so I have this toy
this little keyboard that custom vintage
gave me it's literally like yellow it's
like toy colored yellow and red like as
if it was from Toys R Us we had a patch
on it and I just was like around
and I ran it through uh a plugin called
sketch cassette that I love cassette
that just up the sound more which
made it feel really good but she's
mainly playing along to The Melodies and
it's is so
sad like sorry that's so sad tired wait
keep it and here's how it's interacting
with the
[Music]
lead when it comes to production and
recording instrumental Parts I'm much
more interested in the first pass and
the sort of guesswork that goes into
that I'd much less like to have her sort
of sit there for hours and figure out
exactly what she wants to play for the
verse I want to kind of improvisational
M play the like ending of that one just
the outro
[Music]
yeah
out but it I had to boost it so much to
even have you hear it just now it's so
quiet in the mix also underneath it are
bunch of adlibs that she did but they're
so bar adbs oh my God I could do a whole
interview about adlibs nobody ever asks
me about adlibs they make songs so
special you don't even know
[Music]
dude but they're that quiet they're
so this
one and again under the lead I don't
know how to feel I love that one I don't
know how to
feel love it oh it makes me so excited I
had this idea for the the one on the
second half of the first verse when it
says taking a drive I love this is here
Tak a drive I just wanted it to have
this weird kind of euphoric thing
happening so I I said Woo I recorded
that do you want to hear what it sounds
like with no
plugins I forgot and then I ran it
through an overdrive and a channel EQ
and a Reverb plugin it sounds like
this and then I turned it way down and
it plays at the same time as a big
thumpy um drum a drum hitting and also a
Basse starting and the the three of them
together taking a
drive night it does like an emotional
thing to you I feel the same way about
the little uh what reminds me of like a
Nintendo DS or something which is this
like
arpeggiated
organ I love this I think this does so
much for the S it plays so quietly it
just kind of Peaks out when the vocal
goes away it's so nostalgic to me sounds
it's nostalgic sounds like a it sounds
fake sounds like a barf it's like so
sentimental also a bunch of uh melron
patches it reminds me of like
Sims I really wanted a whole thing to
sound like Animal Crossing I think that
was a big there's some really really
distant huge
[Music]
guitars so cool I love that that's
hidden underneath it's so funny
producing music because when you record
something like that you inherently have
to record it super loud cuz part of the
way that a guitar sounds is the feedback
you have to record it loud enough that
the speaker the pickup on the guitar is
picking up the noise from the speaker so
you're like you're playing your normal
song and you're destroying your song
with this like you know butt rock guitar
part and you know as a producer that
you're like I'm going to Chuck it as far
in the background as humanly possible no
one would ever like think that that's in
there it adds it adds so much yeah
there's Just Energy that that's
providing um and that's sort of the
again that's like the physics of it like
it would never sit in that song If We
Had it you know super loud yeah when we
were writing this we were very very much
writing about you know a character and
we were writing from the perspective of
a character and her life and the way she
sees the world through her eyes and her
experiences and it wasn't until like 2
days later that I was listening to it
and I was like this is me this is my
life and how I feel and it was pretty
weird to like not realize that my
subconscious was doing that and and also
just that I related a lot to this
character I think it's an excuse to be a
little braver than you might be willing
if you are writing something that you
know people are going to receive as
autobiographical so true I think if you
write a lyric like I'm sad again don't
tell my boyfriend and you know your
boyfriend is going to hear it and think
Jesus Christ that takes a different
amount of Courage than being like bar
about you no it's literally not about
you yeah no it's a character that's what
I was I was hitting that the next day
I'm sad
again don't tell my boyfriend
not what
he when we were with Greta we saw the
first 35 40 minutes straight that was
edited at the time and then we saw sort
of moments key moments that she wanted
us to see and we we were shown what at
the time was the scene that the song
ends up in which is the the now feel
scene which made me cry watching that
and at the time had no uh music montage
oh yeah no Montage no life Montage which
later found out as like footage of the
crew and casts family members which is
beautiful but at the time it was just a
one shot of Margot crying in this like
white room but we loved that moment in
that line and she had sort of said we're
missing what she was referring to as
Barbie's heart song yeah so we had all
that in the back of our minds when we
went into write that pressure like
almost doesn't exist when it's just us
to you know in the studio in his house
like you know we're we're eating like
donuts and and like making music and
playing pickle ball and stuff it's just
like the pressure of of whoever the fat
suits are I don't know yeah how do I
quiet the noise I'm not really listening
I'm not really listening the team canest
not to throw Billy under the bus but you
you're asking how she quiets the noise
and Billy's like what's going who's
what's I I don't know what the hell is
going on I'm I have i l little noise
gets in there I have I have
1,461 unread texts right now I'm not
looking at that stuff I never really
questioned the song I was like is that
is that enough of a chorus just like
repeating cuz I cuz I I don't know how
to feel I just was like don't know how
to feel like am I saying enough like
does that convey what I mean and I think
that it so did I was just nervous that
it wasn't you know saying enough but in
a way it was like saying way enough you
know it it was really the perfect like
simple way to be like I don't know what
I'm doing you know I don't know how to
feel I don't and I think that it's
that's kind of one of the most special
parts of the song is just this like
simple like statement that somebody
could just say I've said that I've said
that before in my life I think all of us
have probably been like I don't know how
to feel and literally that she doesn't
know how to feel like physically we made
the song early enough in the um process
of them scoring the film that after we'd
written the song they started using the
Melodies that we'd written for the song
in the film score and so there'd be
scenes where there's an orchestra
playing The Melodies that are in this
song in the film kind of Full Circle the
the orchestra that they'd recorded of
The Melodies of our song that they'd put
in the movie I was like well why can we
get a pass of of the orchestra playing
just sort of chords underneath um the
song so that it sort of ties all into
the film score this is like a breakout
of like the orchestra stems it's like a
million microphones
but there's some
[Music]
horns
marker Andrew who was his uh composing
partner he sent over like like four
tracks he sent over like strings horns
cs80 harp one of my favorite parts that
he added is the ascending
[Music]
harp every time it hits
it oh my God it just it's really I love
that the song means a lot to me it means
a lot to me I think that it's hard to
like listen to I think there's some
things in this world that don't like
they kind of don't stay yours especially
when they are consumed by the public and
things like that and I think that this
song no matter what happens with it I
think it'll always be mine and I'll feel
like it's right here because it is for
me I think it's just about changing and
I think when you grow and when you
change is sort of inherently an identity
crisis that sort of metamorphosis as a
person which is like the most cathartic
important part of living your life and
aging is also this like devastating
experience and can really put you in
crisis growing up is scary yeah and
growing up doesn't stop when you turn 18
or reach the height that you're going to
be for the rest of your life growing up
is just lived experience continuing to
wash over you like waves on a beach
until you're worn smooth like beach
glass and then you die um Jesus Christ
and uh that's
fine